Tess K. Swiecanski Ivoryton, CT 06442 | Tess.Swiecanski@uconn.edu

### **Professional summary**

I am a graduate student at the University of Connecticut and seasonal resource assistant at Connecticut Department of Energy and Environmental Protection. My professional background includes hands on experience and professional training in a variety of environments from military to state agencies. I am interested in pursuing Federal, State, and Non-profit opportunities with a focus in fisheries conservation and management upon graduation.

#### Education

Master of Science in Biodiversity and Conservation Biology | Expected Graduation Date May 2022

University of Connecticut

Bachelor of Science in Marine and Environmental Sciences | 2012 U.S. Coast Guard Academy

## Work experience

Environmental Protection Seasonal Resource Assistant | 2021-Present CT DEEP | Old Lyme, CT

- Assistant to biologists in the Bureau of Natural Resource's Fisheries Division; assisting on the American Shad and Sturgeon Projects.
- Duties include fieldwork on fishing boats using a variety of fishing gear types, laboratory fish processing, processing and aging various fish structures, cleaning and maintaining sampling gear, conducting data entry, and following data quality assurance processes. Fishing gear types include gillnets, trawls, and seines.

Park Ranger | 2020-2020 City of Santa Barbara Parks and Recreation | Santa Barbara, CA

- The Park Ranger program contributes to the Parks and Recreation Department Mission and helps provide citizens with safe, clean, and useable parks and beaches. The Park Ranger promotes safety, educates the public on the history and proper use of City parks, and helps maintain the beauty of the City's treasured natural resources.
- Position works closely with police department, harbor patrol, county rangers, animal control, and life guards.

Admissions Officer | 2017-2019 U.S. Coast Guard Academy | New London, CT

- Admissions officer for the United States Coast Guard Academy. Primary duties include
  high school visits, college fairs, speaking with students and families, briefs, workshops
  hosted at local CG Sectors, reviewing applications, and representing the Coast Guard in a
  positive and professional manner. In this position utilized a variety of presentation
  systems, developed public speaking skills, and positive customer service.
- Received Coast Guard Recruiting Service Ribbon and qualified for CG-HRM 10 (Human Resources) and CG-HRM12 (Recruiting) specialties.

Pollution Responder/Apprentice Marine Inspector | 2014-2017 U.S. Coast Guard | Seattle, WA

- Inspected foreign freighter vessels and domestic small passenger vessels in the Puget Sound AOR. Coordination between vessel masters, local companies, and mariners required. Pollution Responder for the Incident Management Division at Sector Puget Sound. Coordinate with local federal agencies during marine events and spills. Enforcement of National and Area Contingency Plans.
- Obtained qualification as Victim Advocate, advocate for sexual assault victims. Ability to handle sensitive information and develop interpersonal skills during extremely difficult situations.
- Acted as interim Training Officer for Sector Puget Sound. Maintained unit readiness at a superior level for mandated government training, near 100% completion by unit.

Deck Watch Officer | 2012-2014 U.S. Coast Guard | Key West, FL

- Deck Watch Officer onboard CGC MOHAWK, a medium endurance cutter. Primary missions in the District 7 area included drug interdiction, migrant interdiction, search and rescue, and fisheries patrols.
- Acted as landing signal officer for helicopter detachment team deployments. Qualified 2 junior officers as landing signal officers. Required coordination between helicopter pilots, members securing the helicopter, helicopter fueling team, and bridge team.
- Acted as interim department head of the Support Division for a deployment in the Caribbean. Control of 15 division members to ensure continued operations during stressful drug interdiction deployment.

### Skills and certifications

- EEOC Investigator
- EMT Certified
- PC 832 Arrest Certification

#### **Personal interests**

Outside of academics and professional life, I enjoy a variety of physical activities to include yoga, paddle boarding, biking, and hiking. Physical fitness is important to me because of the mental and emotional well-being that comes with being active as well as being able to perform fieldwork with ease.

# **Community service**

Volunteer | 2020 Santa Barbara Humane Society | Santa Barbara, CA

First Responder | 2017-2019 Mystic Aquarium | Mystic, CT

Tutor | 2014-2015 Catholic Community Services Youth Tutoring Program | Seattle, WA